Finding Aid for George N. Carman papers, 1839-1941
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George N. Carman papers 1839-1941
Carman, George N., 1856-1941.
6 linear feet
85875 Aa 2
Educator, director of the Lewis Institute in Chicago, Illinois; professional and personal correspondence, diaries, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Portions of the collection came from George N. Carman (donor no. 451 ). The bulk of the collection came from Milo Quaife (donor no. 1336 ) who had received them from Carman’s niece Bertha Glassbrook.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
George Noble Carman was born on July 18, 1856 in Walworth, Wayne County, New York. He graduated from the University of Michigan in 1881. While studying at the University of Michigan, Carman also taught at Ypsilanti High School. He became principal of the school after receiving his degree. He later became superintendent of schools at Union City, Michigan and principal of the Brooklyn, NY public school No. 15.
In 1889 Carman returned to the Midwest to become principal of the St. Paul Minnesota High School. He was associate professor of English at the University of Chicago and dean of the Morgan Park Academy. In 1893, Carman joined the staff of the University of Chicago as dean of the academy, a position he held until 1895 when he was named first director of Lewis Institute. Lewis Institute merged with Armour Institute of Technology in 1940 to form Illinois Institute of Technology.
Carman was also active in the North Central Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools since its organization in 1895, serving first as its treasurer and since 1903 as president. He was also secretary of the Association's commission on accredited schools which was organized in 1901. He died June 24, 1941.
The George N. Carman collection includes professional and family correspondence, autobiography and related materials, diaries 1875-1880, partly concerning his student life at University of Michigan, genealogical materials, photographs, and miscellanea relating to the Lewis Institute.
Subjects:
Carman, George N., 1856-1941.; Education--Illinois--Chicago.; Lewis Institute.; Schools--Illinois--Chicago.; Teachers--Illinois--Chicago.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1871-1880.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Carman, Ada MacVicar.; Carman, George N., 1856-1941.; Carman family.; Children.; Offices--1891-1900.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Tintypes.
- Correspondence
  - Undated and 1839-1893 (Box 1)
  - 1894-1909 (Box 2)
  - 1910-1921 (Box 3)
  - 1922-1932 (Box 4)
  - 1933-1941 (Box 5)
- Other Material
  - Carman farm materials (Box 5)
  - Income tax returns (Box 5)
  - Autobiography (Box 5)
  - Autobiographical materials (Box 5)
  - Diaries, September 1875-April 1880, 3 volumes (Box 5)
    (include comments on student life at the University of Michigan, courses taken, expenses, reflections on life)
  - Photographs: portraits of Carman, his wife, and other family members; and other miscellaneous photographs., 5 envelopes (Box 5)
  - Genealogy (Box 6)
  - Student papers (Box 6)
  - Graham Taylor articles (Box 6)
  - Miscellanea, largely concerning Lewis Institute (Box 6)